Finding Aid for David Walbridge Kendall papers, 1862-1865, 1891-1924, and 1932-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David Walbridge Kendall papers 1862-1865 1891-1924 1932-1976 1932-1971
Kendall, David Walbridge, 1903-1976.
851708 Aa 2
Attorney, government official; general counsel, later assistant secretary of the treasury, 1955-1957; special counsel to President Eisenhower, 1958-1961; vice president for legal affairs of the Chrysler Corporation, 1962-1968; chairman of the board of incorporators of the National Railroad Passenger Corporation that led to Amtrak. Personal and autobiographical materials; correspondence, 1932-1976; copies of outgoing responses made as special counsel to the president; speeches, articles, scrapbooks, and clippings pertaining to his career and to his political and civic interests; Amtrak files, including memos and minutes of the board of incorporators, also copies of Civil War correspondence of his uncle Austin J. Kendall, 1862-1865, and papers of his father, educator Calvin Kendall, ca. 1890-ca. 1917; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
12 linear feet
Acquisition: The collection (donor no. 4653 ) was the gift of Mr. Kendall; it came to the library in several accessions, 1968-1976.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
David Kendall was a lawyer and respected public servant. From the date of his graduation from Princeton in 1924 up to his death in 1976, Kendall involved himself in an extraordinary number of political, business, civic, and philanthropic endeavors. Nurtured in Kendall by reason of family background and education was a deep-felt responsibility to contribute to his country and to the public welfare. Perhaps best known as general counsel to President Eisenhower and as the man who helped revitalize America's passenger railroad system, Kendall always lent experience, good judgment, and sagacity to whatever task he applied himself. The Kendall papers document the life of a man known and respected by vast legions of friends and colleagues, and widely involved in the public welfare.
David Kendall was born in Indianapolis, Indiana on February 11, 1903, the son of Calvin N. Kendall and Alla Perkins Field Kendall. He received his early education in the primary schools at Princeton, New Jersey, and Phillips Academy at Andover, Massachusetts. He received his B.A. degree from Princeton in 1924 and his LL.B. from the University of Michigan Law School in 1931.
From 1925 to 1928, Kendall was a reporter and editorial writer for the Jackson Citizen Patriot and the Detroit News. After graduation from the UM Law School, he began the practice of law at Jackson, where he was a partner in the firm of McKone, Badgley, Kendall and Domke, where he worked, except for a four-year stint in the military during World War II, until December 31, 1954.
Kendall was a life-long and active Republican. He was a delegate from Michigan to the Republican National Convention in 1936. A dedicated supporter of Arthur Vandenberg, Kendall cherished the hope and worked for the nomination of Michigan's senator as Republican candidate for president. He championed Vandenberg's cause in the presidential elections from 1936 to 1948. In 1946, he served as vice-chairman of Vandenberg's senatorial campaign committee. In 1952, he was assistant to the Michigan Republican state chairman, and from 1953 to 1956, he served as a member of the Republican National Committee. Always deeply involved in politics, Kendall preferred to work behind the scenes, and never stood for office himself.
On January 10, 1955, following his nomination by President Eisenhower, Kendall assumed office as general counsel of the Treasury Department. In July he was nominated and confirmed as assistant secretary of the Treasury. He served there until December 1957, when he joined the Washington law firm of Cummings, Sellers, Reeves, Conner & Kendall. He was there but a few months when Eisenhower appointed him to be his Special Counsel, working in the White House from December 1958 to January 1961.
Following the Kennedy election in 1960, Kendall returned to the practice of law in Washington. In 1962, Kendall was named vice president for legal affairs of the Chrysler Corporation. He served until his 65th birthday in 1968. He then became counsel of the firm of Butzel, Eaman, Long, Gust & Kennedy. In 1971, Kendall was appointed chairman of the board of incorporators of the National Railroad Passenger Corporation, the group responsible for the establishment of the national passenger railroad system that became known as AMTRAK.
David Kendall died December 27, 1976.
The David Kendall collection covers the period of 1932 to 1976. Included with the collection is a small group of earlier family material, principally copies of the Civil War letters of Austin Kendall, DWK's uncle, and papers of his father Calvin Kendall, a teacher and educator, from the turn of the century.
The Kendall papers (12 linear feet) have been arranged into 10 series: Personal, Correspondence, Chronological File (General Counsel to the President), Speech File, Articles, Topical Files, National Railroad Passenger Corporation, Scrapbooks and Newspaper Clippings, Student Papers, and Family Papers.
Subjects:
Amtrak.; Chrysler Corporation.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Jackson (Mich.); Kendall, David Walbridge, 1903-1976.; Law.; Lawyers--United States.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Railroads--United States.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 117th (1862-1865); United States. Dept. of the Treasury.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Kendall, Calvin N.; Kendall, David Walbridge, 1903-1976.; Republican Party (Mich.)
Contributors:
Kendall, Austin J., b. 1842.; Kendall, Calvin N.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal
  The Personal series consists of biographical material, a series of autobiographical letters that Kendall wrote to his grandchildren in the 1970s, photographs, and an undated diary (probably from the 1950s) when Kendall was serving in the Eisenhower administration.
  - Biographical materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical letters written to his grandchildren 1975 (Box 1)
  - Explanatory notes written about his collection (Box 1)
  - Diary account of European visit 1950s (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence covers the period of 1932 to 1976 (bulk dates, 1932 to 1971). Essentially a run of personal correspondence, this series documents Kendall's wide-ranging interests and vast acquaintances. Of some interest are those letters reflecting Kendall's activities with the Republican Party, especially his support of Senator Arthur Vandenberg in his various senatorial campaigns and in his quest for the Republican nomination for president in the 1940s. Though there are some letters from the period when Kendall served in the Eisenhower administration, the researcher should note that official correspondence from the period of his service in the Treasury Department is located in the National Archives, Washington D.C., and that records generated as General Counsel to Eisenhower will be found in the Eisenhower Presidential Library, Abilene, Kansas. This series of correspondence is personal only. Other series, such as Topical Files and National Passenger Railroad Corporation, also contain runs of correspondence.
  - 1932-1959, 34 folders (Box 1)
  - 1960-1974, 33 folders (Box 2)
- Chronological File: General Counsel to the President
  Chronological File (General Counsel to the President) consists of carbon copies of the letters sent out under Kendall's name during the two-year period that DWK served in the White House, 1958-1961. This series has been sampled to show the type of duties that Kendall performed. As it is only one side of the correspondence, the researcher is directed to the Eisenhower Presidential Library for both the incoming letter and DWK's response.
  - November 1958-January 1961, 9 folders (Box 2)
- Speech File
  - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 3)
  - Dated speeches 1954-1976, 51 folders (Box 3)
- Articles
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - re U.S. sea power circa 1940-1942 (Box 3)
  - re Russian air power 1950 (Box 3)
  - re Max Badgley (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files is an artificially constructed series of materials relating to a variety of subjects from all phases of Kendall's career. The files provide some sense of the wide variety of Kendall's civic and philanthropic interests. Most heavily documented is Kendall's support of Republican party issues and candidates, especially when he served with the party's national committee in the 1950s. His party activities from earlier years will be found in the Correspondence series.
  - American Bar Association 1962 (Box 4)
  - Central Intelligence Agency 1955, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Chrysler Corporation
    - 1963 (Box 4)
    - 1964 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Anti-trust action 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Congressional Ethics: Association of the Bar of the City of New York Special Committee on 1968-1970, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - Ditchley Foundation: Anglo-American Law Conference 1964 (Box 4)
  - Episcopal Church, General Division of Laymen's Work (Box 4)
  - Forbes, Malcolm 1958-1959 (applying for position in government) (Box 4)
  - Hutzel Hospital 1975 (Box 4)
  - Jackson Area Industrial Development Corporation 1962 (Box 4)
  - Law practice: partnership agreements, etc. (Box 4)
  - National Agricultural Chemicals Association 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Princeton University (45th reunion booklet of the class of 1924) (Box 4)
  - Princeton University (Carleton Putnam racial views) (Box 4)
  - Republican Party
    - General
      - 1954 (Box 4)
      - 1958-1962 (Box 4)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
      - 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - Fred Alger campaign for governor 1952 (Box 4)
    - Contacts with national administration 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - Papers re criticism of the Eisenhower administration 1953 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Republican Party 1958-1961 (Box 4)
    - National Convention 1960 (Box 4)
    - Romney liaison group 1968 (Box 4)
    - Nixon administration 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Republican Principles Task Force 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1972 campaign (Box 4)
    - American Foundation of the Republican Party (Box 4)
  - U.S. Coast Guard Academy, Advisory Committee 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - U.S. Naval War College 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - World War II miscellanea (Box 4)
- National Railroad Passenger Corporation
  The largest series relates to the National Railroad Passenger Corporation. Kendall served as chairman of the board of incorporators of this organization that was given responsibility for forming into a single system the nation's passenger railroads. Eventually known as AMTRAK, Kendall's work on the board related to the enabling legislation, to the selection of routes that would be serviced under AMTRAK, and to various legislative and court challenges to their choices. Types of materials to be found in this series include correspondence, minutes and other materials given to board members, clippings, subject files, and published material.
  - Volume containing NRPC agreement, NRPC arbitration agreement, bylaws, and articles of incorporation (Box 5)
  - NRPC agreement March 25, 1971 (draft) (Box 5)
  - Incorporators meetings summaries December 1970-March 1971 (Box 5)
  - Agenda January-April 1971 (Box 5)
  - Briefing manual (Box 5)
  - Briefing book April 6, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors minute book December 1970-May 1971, 1 folders (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors meetings April-May 1971 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee meetings April 1971 (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors meetings July 1971-August 1973 (some gaps) (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors meetings September-November 1973, March 1974 (Box 6)
  - Topical Files
    - Appointments (Box 6)
    - Auto-Train (Box 6)
    - Budget and financial papers (Box 6)
    - Congress (statements, criticisms, bills) (Box 6)
    - Consultants (Box 6)
    - Employment (Box 6)
    - Executive Compensation Committee (Box 6)
    - Grant agreement (Box 6)
    - Harris (Louis) survey (Box 6)
    - Historical/financial information (Box 6)
    - Liability/Casualty (Box 6)
    - Litigation
      - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Indiana Arbitration Award (Box 6)
      - Kansas City Terminal Railway Company (Box 6)
      - National Arbitration Panel case no. 2 re station costs (Box 6)
      - Penn Central Transportation Company compensation case (Box 6)
    - Metropolitan Transportation Authority (Box 6)
    - National Association of Railroad Passengers (Box 6)
    - New England Corridor (Box 6)
    - Observations and critiques (Box 6)
    - Office of Management and Budget (Box 6)
    - Operations (Box 6)
    - Pullman contracts (Box 7)
    - Review of AMTRAK (Box 7)
    - Route selection (Box 7)
    - Statutes and basic contract (Box 7)
    - Turbotrains (Box 7)
    - Weicker, Lowell (Box 7)
    - Weinberger, Caspar (Box 7)
  - DWK statements and speeches (Box 7)
  - Statements and speeches of others (mainly Roger Lewis) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1971-1976, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - DWK resignation from AMTRAK (and Richard M. Nixon response) (Box 7)
  - Annual reports and other published materials (mainly government documents) relating to the National Railroad Passenger Corporation (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to the passage of the National Railroad Passenger Corporation legislation and the first months of AMTRAK's operation (Box 9)
- Scrapbooks And Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks relate primarily to Kendall's service to the Republican party and in the Eisenhower administration.
  - Volumes and loose clippings detailing his career and professional activities (Box 10)
- Student Papers
  The Student Papers series includes student essays and notebooks written by Kendall while a student at Princeton and at the University of Michigan Law School.
  - Princeton University, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Law School, 3 folders; 1 volumes (Box 11)
- Family Papers
  The final series - Family Papers - consists of materials preserved by Kendall of his father and of his father's brother, Austin. Austin J. Kendall (born 1842) served during the Civil War served with the 117th New York Infantry. The subseries of his papers consists of photocopies of typescripts of the letters that he wrote about his wartime experiences in the period of 1862-1865. Kendall saw service in South Carolina and Virginia, participating in the Petersburg campaign.
  David Kendall's father, Calvin N. Kendall (1858-1921) was a distinguished educator, who served as superintendent of schools in Jackson and Saginaw, Michigan and in New Haven, Connecticut, and Indianapolis, Indiana. He held this later position from 1900 to 1911. He next went on to become commissioner of education for the state of New Jersey (1911-1921). The Calvin Kendall subseries consists of clippings about him, and articles and speeches written mainly on educational topics.
  - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 12)
  - Austin J. Kendall (DWK's uncle)
    - Typescripts of Civil War letters 1862-1865, 1873, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Calvin Kendall (DWK's father)
    - Biographical material and letter 1915 (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Speeches and articles, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Citations, etc. (Box 12)